Jorge Ortiz, Ph.D.

[94 Brett Road, Piscataway, NJ 08854-8058]

jortiz@alum.mit.edu http://jorgeortizphd.info

Research Interests

My research research is in applied machine learning for sensor-based systems with a focus on sustainability and healthcare. I am interested how information is exchanged between humans and physically engineered systems and how to use this two-way exchange to improve both human quality of life and system outcomes.

Education

University of California, Berkeley

Berkeley, CA

Doctor of Philosophy in Computer Science;

May. 2010 - Dec. 2013

- Dissertation: A Platform Architecture for Sensor Data Processing and Verification in Buildings

University of California, Berkeley

Berkeley, CA

Masters of Science in Computer Science;

Aug. 2007 - May 2010

- Thesis: Multichannel Reliability Assessment in Real World WSNs
- Relevant Courses: Advanced Systems Seminar I & II, Graduate Networking, Sensor Networks Seminar,
 Combinatorial Algorithms, Parallel Computation Algorithms, Statistical Learning Theory, Practical Machine Learning.

Massachusetts Institute of Technology

Cambridge, MA

Bachelors of Science in Computer Science and Engineering:

Aug. 1999 - May 2003

- Thesis: Connection Oriented Routing Environment (CORE): A Generalized Device Interconnect

Academic Appointments

Rutgers University

New Brunswick, NJ August 2018 – Present

Assistant Professor

Honors and Invited Talks

- Invited speaker at NSF Workshop on the Dynamic Interaction of Embodied Human and Machine Intelligence, May 2019
- Invited speaker ECE Seminar at Emory University, February 2019
- **Keynote speaker** Workshop on Smart and Connected Indoor Environments in conjunction with IEEE International Conference on Sensing, Communication and Networking (SECON 2017)
- Qualcomm Innovation Fellowship Finalist 2011
- NSF Graduate Fellowship Honorable Mention 2008
- Ford Foundation Diversity Fellowship Honorable Mention 2008

Conferences and Journals

- [1] Raghu Ganti, Mudhakar Srivatsa, Dakshi Agrawal, Petros Zerfos, and **Jorge Ortiz**. "MP-trie: Fast Spatial Queries on Moving Objects". In: *Proceedings of the Industrial Track of the 17th International Middleware Conference*. Middleware Industry '16. Trento, Italy: ACM, 2016, 1:1–1:6.
- [2] **Jorge Ortiz**, Catherine Crawford, and Franck Le. "DeviceMien: Network Device Behavior Modeling for Identifying Unknown IoT Devices (**Best Paper Finalist**)". In: ACM/IEEE Conference on Internet of Things Design and Implementation. ACM, 2019.
- [3] Shiqiang Wang and **Jorge Ortiz**. "Non-negative matrix factorization of signals with overlapping events for event detection applications". In: *The 42nd IEEE International Conference on Acoustics*, Speech and Signal Processing ICASSP 2017. 2017.
- [4] Dezhi Hong, Hongning Wang, **Jorge Ortiz**, and Kamin Whitehouse. "The Building Adapter: Towards Quickly Applying Building Analytics at Scale (**Best Paper Finalist, 2nd Highest Review Score**)". In: *Proceedings of the 2nd ACM International Conference on Embedded Systems for Energy-Efficient Built Environments*. BuildSys '15. Seoul, South Korea: ACM, 2015, pp. 123–132.
- [5] Arka A. Bhattacharya, Dezhi Hong, David Culler, **Jorge Ortiz**, Kamin Whitehouse, and Eugene Wu. "Automated Metadata Construction to Support Portable Building Applications (**Best Paper Finalist, 1st Highest Review Score**)". In: *Proceedings of the 2nd ACM International Conference on Embedded Systems for Energy-Efficient Built Environments*. BuildSys '15. Seoul, South Korea: ACM, 2015, pp. 3–12.
- [6] Chien-Chin Huang, Qi Chen, Zhaoguo Wang, Russell Power, Jorge Ortiz, Jinyang Li, and Zhen Xiao. "Spartan: A Distributed Array Framework with Smart Tiling". In: 2015 USENIX Annual Technical Conference (USENIX ATC 15). Santa Clara, CA: USENIX Association, 2015, pp. 1–15.
- [7] Romain Fontugne, **Jorge Ortiz**, Nicolas Tremblay, Pierre Borgnat, Patrick Flandrin, Kensuke Fukuda, David Culler, and Hiroshi Esaki. "Strip, Bind, and Search: A Method for Identifying Abnormal Energy Consumption in Buildings". In: *Proceedings of the 12th International Conference on Information Processing in Sensor Networks*. IPSN '13. Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, USA, 2013, pp. 129–140.
- [8] Jorge Ortiz and David Culler. "Multichannel Reliability Assessment in Real World WSNs". In: Proceedings of the 9th ACM/IEEE International Conference on Information Processing in Sensor Networks. IPSN '10. Stockholm, Sweden: ACM, 2010, pp. 162–173.
- [9] Jorge Ortiz, C.R. Baker, Daekyeong Moon, R. Fonseca, and I. Stoica. "Beacon Location Service: A Location Service for Point-to-Point Routing in Wireless Sensor Networks". In: Information Processing in Sensor Networks, 2007. IPSN 2007. 6th International Symposium on. 2007, pp. 166–175.
- [10] Stephen Dawson-Haggerty, Xiaofan Jiang, Gilman Tolle, Jorge Ortiz, and David Culler. "sMAP: A Simple Measurement and Actuation Profile for Physical Information". In: Proceedings of the 8th ACM Conference on Embedded Networked Sensor Systems. SenSys '10. Zurich, Switzerland: ACM, 2010, pp. 197–210. ISBN: 978-1-4503-0344-6.
- [11] Mehdi Maasoumy, **Jorge Ortiz**, David Culler, and Alberto Sangiovanni-Vincentelli. "Flexibility of Commercial Building HVAC Fan as Ancillary Service for Smart Grid". In: *IEEE Green Energy and Smart Systems Conference*. 2013.

Workshops, Demos and Technical Reports

- [1] Stephen Dawson-Haggerty, **Jorge Ortiz**, Xiaofan Fred Jiang, and David E. Culler. "The Effect of Link Churn on Wireless Routing". In: UCB/EECS-2008-109 (2008). URL: http://www2.eecs.berkeley.edu/Pubs/TechRpts/2008/EECS-2008-109.html.
- [2] Wei-Han Lee, **Jorge Ortiz**, Bongjun Ko, and Ruby B. Lee. "Time Series Segmentation through Automatic Feature Learning". In: *CoRR* abs/1801.05394 (2018). arXiv: 1801.05394. URL: http://arxiv.org/abs/1801.05394.
- [3] Xiaofan Jiang, Jay Taneja, **Jorge Ortiz**, Arsalan Tavakoli, Prabal Dutta, Jaein Jeong, David Culler, Philip Levis, and Scott Shenker. "An Architecture for Energy Management in Wireless Sensor Networks". In: *SIGBED Rev.* 4.3 (July 2007), pp. 31–36.
- [4] Jorge Ortiz. "A Platform Architecture for Sensor Data Processing and Verification in Buildings". In: UCB/EECS-2013-196 (2013). URL: http://www2.eecs.berkeley.edu/Pubs/TechRpts/2013/EECS-2013-196.html.
- [5] "An information-centric energy infrastructure: The Berkeley view". In: Sustainable Computing: Informatics and Systems 1.1 (2011), pp. 7–22.
- [6] Arsalan Tavakoli, Prabal Dutta, Jaein Jeong, Sukun Kim, **Jorge Ortiz**, David Culler, Phillip Levis, and Scott Shenker. "A Modular Sensornet Architecture: Past, Present, and Future Directions". In: *SIGBED Rev.* 4.3 (July 2007), pp. 49–54. ISSN: 1551-3688. DOI: 10.1145/1317103.1317112. URL: http://doi.acm.org/10.1145/1317103.1317112.
- [7] **Jorge Ortiz** and David Culler. "Exploring Diversity: Evaluating the Cost of Frequency Diversity in Communication and Routing (**Best Poster Award**)". In: SenSys '08 (2008), pp. 411–412.
- [8] Arka Bhattacharya, David E. Culler, **Jorge Ortiz**, Dezhi Hong, and Kamin Whitehouse. "Enabling Portable Building Applications through Automated Metadata Transformation". In: UCB/EECS-2014-159 (2014). URL: http://www2.eecs.berkeley.edu/Pubs/TechRpts/2014/EECS-2014-159.html.
- [9] Jorge Ortiz. "A System for Managing Physical Data in Buildings". In: UCB/EECS-2010-128 (2010). Ed. by David E. Culler. URL: http://www2.eecs.berkeley.edu/Pubs/TechRpts/2010/EECS-2010-128.html.
- [10] Dezhi Hong, Jorge Ortiz, Arka Aloke Bhattacharya, and Kamin Whitehouse. "Sensor-Type Classification in Buildings". In: CoRR abs/1509.00498 (2015). URL: http://arxiv.org/abs/1509.00498.
- [11] Stephen Dawson-Haggerty, **Jorge Ortiz**, Xiaofan Jiang, Jeff Hsu, Sushant Shankar, and David Culler. "Enabling Green Building Applications". In: HotEmNets '10 (2010), 4:1–4:5.
- [12] Arka Bhattacharya, David Culler, Dezhi Hong, Kamin Whitehouse, and **Jorge Ortiz**. "Automated Metadata Transformation for A-priori Deployed Sensor Networks". In: SenSys '14 (2014), pp. 364–365.
- [13] Maanit Mehra, Aditya Bagri, **Jorge Ortiz**, and Xiaofan Jiang. "Image Analysis for Identifying Mosquito Breeding Grounds". In: IoTPDA '16 (2016).
- [14] **Jorge Ortiz**, Chien-Chin Huang, and Supriyo Chakraborty. "Fast Image Clustering on Network of Mobile Phones". In: ICML '16 (2016).
- [15] **Jorge Ortiz** and Younghun Kim. "Project Tidy: Ranking Time Series for Smart Energy Systems: Poster Abstract". In: BuildSys '16 (2016).
- [16] Bong Jun Ko, **Jorge Ortiz**, Theodoros Salonidis, Maroun Touma, Dinesh Verma, Shiqiang Wang, Xiping Wang, and David Wood. "Acoustic Signal Processing for Anomaly Detection in Machine Room Environments: Demo Abstract". In: BuildSys '16 (2016).

- [17] S. Lanzisera, S. Dawson-Haggerty, X. Jiang, H. Y. Cheung, J. Taneja, J. Lai, J. Ortiz, D. Culler, and R. Brown. "Wireless electricity metering of miscellaneous and electronic devices in buildings". In: (2011), pp. 16–19. DOI: 10.1109/FIIW.2011.6476843.
- [18] Dezhi Hong, **Jorge Ortiz**, Kamin Whitehouse, and David Culler. "Towards Automatic Spatial Verification of Sensor Placement in Buildings". In: BuildSys'13 (2013), 13:1–13:8.
- [19] **Jorge Ortiz**, Yongwoo Noh, Gavin Saldanha, David Su, and David Culler. "Towards Real-time, Fine-grained Energy Analytics in Buildings Through Mobile Phones". In: BuildSys '12 (2012).
- [20] Jeff Hsu, Prashanth Mohan, Xiaofan Jiang, **Jorge Ortiz**, Sushant Shankar, Stephen Dawson-Haggerty, and David Culler. "HBCI: Human-building-computer Interaction". In: BuildSys '10 (2010), pp. 55–60.

Service

- 1. CPS-IoT Week 2019 Publication Chair (HSCC, ICCPS, IPSN, RTAS, IoTDI)
- 2. Richard Tapia Celebration in Diversity Poster Co-Chair 2018, Chair 2019
- 3. TPC Member Latinos in Artificial Intelligence Workshop NeurIPS 2018, ICML 2019
- 4. TPC Member Energy Data and Analytics Workshop at e-Energy 2018, 2019
- 5. TPC Member Sensys 2016 (Demo Session),
- 6. TPC Member IPSN 2014, 2017
- 7. TPC Member Buildsys 2016, 2017, 2018, 2019
- 8. Organizing Committee Sensys/Buildsys 2016, 2017
- 9. The 26th International Conference on Computer Communication and Networks (ICCCN 2017)
- 10. TPC Member 1st Workshop on Smart and Connected Indoor Environments (SCIE) in conjunction with IEEE International Conference on Sensing, Communication and Networking (SECON 2017)
- 11. TPC Member 1st Workshop on Internet of Thing Physical Data Analytics (IoTPDA) in conjunction with IEEE International Conference on Sensing, Communication and Networking (SECON 2016)
- 12. TPC Member DCOSS 2016 (The annual International Conference on Distributed Computing in Sensor Systems)
- 13. TPC Member ALGOSENSORS 2017
- 14. TPC IEEE workshop on Big Data Management for the Internet of Things (BIOT2017)
- Member of CSGSA Faculty Candidate Evaluation Committee, UCB Computer Science Div. (2008, 2009, 2010)
- 16. President of CSGSA Faculty Candidate Evaluation Committee, UCB Computer Science Div. (2011)
- 17. Chair, Internet of Things Professional Interest Community (IoT-PIC) IBM Research at Watson Labs.

Patents

References

- [1] Jorge J Ortiz Theodoros Salonidis Rahul Urgaonkar Dinesh C Verma Xiping Wang Xiping Wang Keith William Grueneberg Bong Jun Ko. "Extending cloud computing to on-premises data". Patent US 9342357 (US). May 2016.
- [2] Jorge J Ortiz Theodoros Salonidis Rahul Urgaonkar Dinesh C Verma Xiping Wang Xiping Wang Keith W Grueneberg Bong Jun Ko. "Matching untagged data sources to untagged data analysis applications". Patent US 14/743,130 (US). June 2015.

Industry Experience

IBM Research

• Research Staff Member

Yorktown Heights, NY Dec. 2013 – Aug. 2018

 Research work on systems and algorithms for physical analytics in buildings and IoT, deploying machine learning on resource constrained devices, and distributed systems and algorithms for large-scale machine learning applications.

Spire

San Francisco, CA

Jan. 2013 - Sept. 2013

Senior Software Engineer

Designed and wrote communication kernel for arduino-based, nano satellites.

Oracle Corporation

Software Engineer

Burlington, MA

Sept. 2003 – Feb. 2007

 Assisted in designing, debugging, and maintaining several features in Oracle Enterprise Planning and Budgeting (EPB) software suite; include, but not limited to the setup of PL/SQL packages, schemas, and interfaces to the Javabased UI.

References

Prof. David E. Culler

CS Division University of California, Berkeley 465 Soda Hall Berkeley, CA culler@cs.berkeley.edu

Prof. Prabal Dutta

EECS University of California, Berkeley 550C Cory Hall prabal@berkeley.edu

Prof. Randy Katz

CS Division University of California, Berkeley 775 Soda Hall Berkeley, CA randy@cs.berkeley.edu

Prof. Xiaofan (Fred) Jiang

ECE Columbia University 1008 Northwest Corner Building jiang@ee.columbia.edu

Dr. Catherine Crawford

Distinguished Engineer Cognitive Internet of Things IBM Research catcraw@us.ibm.com

Prof. Jay Taneja

ECE UMASS, Amherst 309C Knowles Engineering Bldg jtaneja@umass.edu